Crossing 7 Peaks Alone: The Taiwan Mountains Where 4 Hikers Went Missing
白姑大山七峰纵走｜在四个失踪案例发生的山区独攀
Petr: climb Malunshan and Baigu
Petr：爬马仑山和白姑大山
This is the story of my attempt to reach all seven peaks of Baigu Mountain above 3000 meters.
这是我尝试登顶白姑大山海拔3000公尺以上七座山峰的故事。
It reminded me why preparation matters in the mountains.
它提醒了我为什么在山里的准备很重要。
I hiked this direction for the first time, but I was in this area several times before for searching for missing hikers.
我第一次走这个方向，但我之前曾多次在这个区域搜寻失踪的登山者。
I started alone from Guguan (谷關) in March 2025.
2025年3月，我独自一人从谷关出发。
The weather was still cold, so I packed extra gear.
天气还很冷，所以我多带了一些装备。
My goal: climb all seven peaks of Baigu in one push.
我的目标：一次完成白姑大山全部七座山峰。
Most people take the main trail from the other side, but I chose the harder route and cross whole area.
大多数人从另一边走主要步道，但我选择了更难的路线并穿越整个区域。
Through Malun Mountain (馬崙山), over the Malun Baigu Trail (馬崙白姑步道), and leave on the east side.
经过马仑山，越过马仑白姑步道，从东侧离开。
The first section goes through Malunshan Trail (馬崙山步道).
第一段路线经过马仑山步道。
It's initial 6km warm up with 1200m elevation gain.
这是最初6公里的暖身，爬升1200公尺。
It's maintained but steep.
步道有维护但很陡。
On the way you can see some man made ruins and bit of history.
沿途可以看到一些人造遗迹和一些历史。
As I joke: past garbage becomes "artifacts" in the present day.
就像我开玩笑说的：过去的垃圾在今天变成了“文物”。
I used our Tornado vest pack,
我使用了我们的BEAST VEST PACK 疾行登山背心背包，
which we developed with Hanchor for light packing in Taiwan mountains.
这是我们与Hanchor合作开发的，专为台湾山区轻量化登山设计。
It's up to 32 liters capacity, but enough space for several days.
容量最多32公升，但足够装几天的装备。
The vest fits to the body
背心贴合身体
and keeps everything accessible with some smart features
并且让所有东西都容易取用，有一些巧妙的设计
as shoulder pocket for inReach mini.
例如肩带上有放inReach mini的口袋。
You can find it at www.beast.run.
你可以在www.beast.run找到它。
This direction is not popular.
这个方向不受欢迎。
Very long climb on day one,
第一天爬升非常长，
dense bamboo sections which are hard to navigate in,
密集的箭竹路段很难导航，
and no reliable water sources.
而且没有可靠的水源。
Average hiker cannot finish it in one day.
一般登山者无法在一天内完成。
Near the top of Malun Mountain (馬崙山), I always remember July 2022.
在马仑山顶附近，我总是记得2022年7月。
A hiker went missing here for over a week.
一位登山者在这里失踪了一个多星期。
I was on a long trip in the mountains before I came down and could join the search.
我在山里进行长途旅行之后才下山参加搜救。
I was tired and just wished the search is solved soon.
我很累，只希望搜救能尽快解决。
Something guided me from the top of Malun which is 2,305 meters high, deep into the creek system.
有什么东西引导我从海拔2305公尺的马仑山顶，深入到溪谷。
Down to Malun River (馬崙溪) at 1,730 meters.
下到海拔1730公尺的马仑溪。
I found him drowned under a waterfall.
我发现他溺毙在瀑布下。
We'll never know exactly what happened, but most likely he took the wrong direction at the summit.
我们永远不会确切知道发生了什么，但很可能他在山顶走错了方向。
Realized his mistake and tried to descend randomly to escape the mountains.
意识到自己的错误后，试图随意下切离开山区。
This is always wrong.
这总是错误的。
Today we have GPS devices - smartphone apps with offline maps.
现在我们有GPS设备 - 具有离线地图的智能手机应用程序。
Too many cases could be avoided.
太多案例本可以避免。
Followers from overseas often comment about the importance of paper maps, which I am aware of.
国外的追踪者经常评论纸质地图的重要性，我知道这一点。
But in reality, I plan my trip on paper and computer maps, and then use GPS navigation.
但实际上，我在纸质和电脑地图上规划行程，然后使用GPS导航。
So I carry at least two GPS devices as my GPS watch, phone, or inReach2.
所以我至少携带两个GPS设备，如我的GPS手表、手机或inReach2。
The mountains don't forgive navigation mistakes.
山，不会原谅任何导航的失误。
The hardest section starts after Malun Mountain - climbing to Baigu Mountain West Peak (白姑大山西峰).
最难的路段从马仑山之后开始 - 爬升到白姑大山西峰。
Recently, volunteers did amazing work here -
最近，志愿者们在这里做了很棒的工作 -
they installed safety ropes, built rainwater collection points,
他们安装了安全绳索，建盖了雨水收集点，
and placed red guide strings through the bamboo.
并在箭竹中放置了红色引导绳。
Maybe three or four kilometers of string.
可能有三到四公里的绳子。
Petr: charge my phone (old electric pole)
Petr：充电（旧电线杆）
It's hard to imagine how much effort humans spent to access these mountain areas to log trees.
很难想象人们花了多少努力才能进入这些山区砍伐树木。
The scenery was amazing and I was lucky for the weather.
景色令人惊叹，我很幸运遇到好天气。
There was a view to another side of valley
可以看到山谷另一侧的景色
with Jiuxian Shan (九仙山) and Jilong Shan (基隆山) which are almost 3000 meters and also not easy to reach.
包括九仙山和基隆山，它们接近3000公尺，也不容易到达。
In this long climb were many rocky sections, which made it quite interesting and also unique for Taiwan.
在这段漫长的攀登中有许多岩石路段，这使它相当有趣，对台湾来说也很独特。
In Taiwan most hikes are in deep forest with lack of views,
在台湾，大多数登山路线都在缺乏视野的深林中，
but here is pretty, but hard.
这里很美，但非常困难。
Taiwan has 285 peaks over 3000 meters.
台湾有285座超过3000公尺的山峰。
Most hikers know the famous Baiyue (台灣百岳) - the hundred peaks.
大多数登山者都知道著名的台湾百岳。
But there are many more that just few people climb.
但还有更多只有少数人攀登的山峰。
After this trip, I've reached about 240 of them.
这次旅行后，我已经登顶了大约240座。
I was prepared for snow or wet bamboo.
我准备好应对雪或湿箭竹。
I brought waterproof jacket and pants, and waterproof socks.
我带了防水外套和裤子，还有防水袜子。
And warm waterproof gloves - Showa 282
还有保暖防水手套 - Showa 282
Showa gloves look like you are about to clean toilets,
Showa手套看起来像是要去清洁厕所，
but the visage is compensated with functions.
但外观由功能来弥补。
These gloves come in two versions - 281 without warm layer
这些手套有两个版本 - 281没有保暖层
282 with warm layer.
282有保暖层。
I use 281, but for winter hikes I bought 282
我使用281，但对于冬季登山我买了282
which I also used for some winter bike rides.
我也用它进行一些冬季骑行。
This trip, I luckily didn't need them.
这次旅行，我幸运地不需要使用到它们。
Both are waterproof, breathable, and inexpensive.
两者都是防水、透气且便宜。
Small tip: my hands aren't huge,
小提示：我的手不大，
but L size feels small, so I chose LL size.
但L号感觉小，所以我选择了LL号。
You may wonder why I talk about gloves
你可能想知道为什么我谈论手套
and not about other waterproof gear.
而不是其他防水装备。
But reality is that my hands get cold quickly
但现实是我的手很快就会变冷
and it's hard to warm them,
而且很难让它们暖和起来，
especially when everything around you is wet, as often is bamboo in Taiwan.
特别是当你周围的一切都是湿的，就像台湾的箭竹经常那样。
Round 2
第二回合
The Bamboo Battle
箭竹大战
First, I detoured south to West-South Peak of Baigu Mountain (白姑大山西南峰).
首先，我向南绕道到白姑大山西南峰。
On the map, just 900 meters, but it took me 1.5 hours in one direction and then back.
在地图上只有900公尺，但我花了1.5小时走单程然后返回。
Incredibly dense bamboo, not much marking.
极其密集的箭竹，没有多少路标。
You may notice my fancy goggles, last what you need here is poked eye.
你可能会注意到我的时髦护目镜，这里你最不需要的就是眼睛被戳伤。
I was thinking about the purpose of life while pushing through that bamboo.
我在穿过那些箭竹时思考着生命的意义。
Petr: Oh... West-South Peak. Oh My God this is crazy.
Petr：哦...西南峰。天啊，这太疯狂了。
Petr: That was not easy. 900m and 1.5 hour.
Petr：那不容易。900公尺和1.5小时。
(Just checking little bit behind peak)
（只是检查山峰后面一点）
(I let water here. And lost my trekking pole.)
（我把水留在这里了。还丢了我的登山杖。）
Petr:  So cool here.
Petr：这里真酷。
I continued to Baigu Mountain Three-Forked Peak (白姑大山三叉峰),
我继续前往白姑大山三叉峰，
and finally reached the main trail (白姑大山徑) from the other side.
终于从另一侧到达了主步道白姑大山径。
Petr: YES. Crazy, 11 hours.
Petr：好！太疯狂了，11小时。
This leads to the main peak.
这条路通向主峰。
I was prepared for snow or wet bamboo, but the weather was perfect.
我准备好应对雪或湿箭竹，但天气很完美。
Clear sky, but it was getting late.
天空晴朗，但天色已晚。
I decided to sleep on top of Baigu Mountain (白姑大山).
我决定在白姑大山顶上过夜。
Day one: 19 kilometers, 3,250 meters elevation gain, over 11.5 hours.
第一天：19公里，爬升3250公尺，超过11.5小时。
Most hikers cannot complete this direction in one day.
大多数登山者无法在一天内完成这个方向。
I carried all my water from Guguan (谷關) and still had enough for the night and morning.
我从谷关背了所有的水，晚上和早上还有足够的水。
Petr: Bai Gu Da Shan 白姑大山
Petr：白姑大山
I don't recommend sleeping on top of mountain or open space.
我不建议在山顶或开阔空间睡觉。
It's always better to sleep under some vegetation.
在植被下睡觉总是更好。
But if you do, you have to have good weather and know what to do if something is turning wrong.
但如果你这样做，你必须有好天气，并知道如果出问题该怎么做。
I don't like spending money on gear I don't need, but years ago I invested in good sleep gear.
我不喜欢在不需要的装备上花钱，但几年前我投资了好的睡眠装备。
Good 20F down sleeping bag, short inflatable mat, quality bivy and tarp.
好的20F羽绒睡袋、短充气睡垫、优质露宿袋和天幕。
My whole sleep system weighs under 1,200 grams.
我整个睡眠装备总重量不到1200克。
Sleeping under tarp is not for everyone,
天幕下睡觉不适合每个人，
but it's one way to shave weight of sleeping gear and it has also benefits.
但这是减轻睡眠装备重量的一种方法，也有其好处。
But for tonight I even didn't build the tarp.
但今晚我甚至没有搭天幕。
It's really important to have good sleep if possible.
如果可能的话，有良好的睡眠真的很重要。
The night was so peaceful and surprisingly not windy.
夜晚非常平静，令人惊讶的是没有风。
I slept well.
我睡得很好。
I woke up not so early because I wanted to enjoy sunrise on top of Baigu (白姑大山).
我起得不太早，因为我想在白姑大山顶欣赏日出。
It was stunning.
太壮观了。
After packing, I continued down the main trail
收拾好后，我沿著主步道继续下山
steep descent with rock ravine at the bottom.
陡峭的下坡，底部有岩石峡谷。
In the end of 2020, one hiker went ahead of his group.
2020年底，一位登山者走在他的队伍前面。
At the ravine, instead of turning right,
在峡谷处，他没有右转，
he continued left down into the stones and to the creek.
而是继续向左下到石头和溪谷中。
SAR units searched for him - they found an SOS label made from stones down in the creek,
搜救队搜寻他 - 他们在溪谷中发现了用石头做的SOS标记，
just before a high waterfall.
就在一个高瀑布之前。
But the hiker was never found.
但这位登山者从未被找到。
I personally didn't join many searching missions that time
我个人当时没有参加很多搜救任务
and the case was complicated with snow.
而且这个案例因为雪而变得复杂。
I just realized back in July 2020 when I was still young and fast,
我刚刚想起来，2020年7月当我还年轻且快速的时候，
I did fast ascent and descent on main course in 5 hours 15 minutes.
我在主线上快速上升和下降用了5小时15分钟。
These are new reflective markers,
这些是新的反光标记，
added to the main trail after the incidents.
在这些事件后添加到主步道上。
It reminds me of another SAR story from 2021.
这让我想起了2021年另一个搜救故事。
I found a missing senior hiker very deep in a creek near Sanzui Mountain (三錐山).
我在三锥山附近的溪谷深处发现了一位失踪的年长登山者。
(sound of helicopter)
（直升机声音）
Another case of someone getting lost from their group.
又一个从队伍中走失的案例。
It always reminds me: whether you go alone or in a group,
这总是提醒我：无论你是独自一人还是在团队中，
each member should be prepared and should know how to navigate alone.
每个成员都应该准备好并知道如何独自导航。
It's very easy for less experienced hikers to get lost from the group.
经验较少的登山者很容易从队伍中走失。
Not always the slowest person,
不一定是最慢的人，
sometimes even fit hikers go ahead and get lost.
有时甚至体能好的登山者走在前面也会迷路。
Petr: I found him. I was almost going back.
Petr：我找到他了。我几乎要回头了。
Petr: Mr. Huang
Petr：黄先生
Sorry... Sorry...
对不起...对不起...
This was my first time finding a dead hiker alone
这是我第一次独自发现死去的登山者
and it was very tough terrain.
而且是非常艰难的地形。
It's always shocking.
这总是令人震惊的。
Petr : I don't understand how he got here.
Petr：我不明白他怎么到这里的。
Petr: I have so much difficulty go here.
Petr：我要到这里都这么困难。
Since then, during my solo searches, I've found many more,
从那时起，在我的单独搜索中，我发现了更多，
unfortunately many deaths.
不幸的是很多死者。
Petr: Never Go Down!
Petr：永远不要往下走！
But what's worse - some missing were never found.
但更糟糕的是 - 有些失踪者从未被找到。
I continued over Baigu Southeast Peak (白姑東南峰) to the grassland with black pools Siyan Chi campsite (司晏池營地).
我继续经过白姑东南峰到有黑水池的草地司晏池营地。
I was out of water and needed water for today and tonight.
我没有水了，需要今天和今晚的水。
The next section would be hard,
下一段会很困难，
and I wasn't sure I could finish before dark.
我不确定能否在天黑前完成。
I use a Sawyer filter and two water bags - Evernew 2-liter bags (EVERNEW 水袋 2L).
我使用Sawyer滤水器和两个水袋 - Evernew 2公升水袋。
One for dirty water, one for clean.
一个装脏水，一个装干净水。
The trick: use an adapter screw to coupling filter with bags,
诀窍：使用转接器将滤水器与水袋连接，
and set up gravitational filtering instead of squeezing.
并设置重力过滤而不是挤压。
Hang it and let gravity work - very dirty water becomes relatively clean.
挂起来让重力工作 - 非常脏的水会变得相对干净。
Drinkable without boiling.
不用煮沸就能喝。
At least I had not any stomach difficulties due to drinking bad water.
至少我没有因为喝不好的水而出现胃部问题。
I continued straight into dense bamboo toward my sixth and seventh peaks.
我直接进入密集的箭竹，朝着我的第六和第七座山峰前进。
Baigu Mountain Middle Peak (白姑大山中峰) and far one - Baigu Mountain East Peak (白姑大山東峰).
白姑大山中峰和远处的 - 白姑大山东峰。
Petr:  This considred to be highway.
Petr：这被认为是高速公路。
There was even an open area, quite pretty with fine black pool.
甚至有一个开阔区域，相当漂亮，有一个好的黑水池。
Black pool water is really dirty and can clog filters badly.
黑水池的水真的很脏，会严重堵塞滤水器。
I tried various filters - Katadyn BeFree is useless for high mountain trips in Taiwan, it clogs terribly.
我试过各种滤水器 - Katadyn BeFree对台湾高山行程来说毫无用处，堵塞得很厉害。
I tried smaller Sawyer versions too,
我也试过较小的Sawyer版本，
but the best is their biggest classic filter - SP129.
但最好的是他们最大最典型的滤水器 - SP129。
Just remember to flush it in reverse with clean water after each trip.
只要记得在每次旅行后用干净的水反向冲洗。
And don't let your filter freeze - put it in your sleeping bag during winter nights.
不要让你的滤水器结冰 - 在冬季夜晚把它放在睡袋里。
Same with electronics - keep your phone and any batteries in your sleeping bag too.
电子产品也一样 - 也要把手机和任何电池放在睡袋里。
Your phone doesn't need to be off for the night,
你的手机晚上不需要关机，
but put it in airplane mode to preserve the battery.
但把它设为飞行模式以保存电池。
I reached Baigu Mountain Middle Peak (白姑大山中峰) - not as bad as expected.
我到达了白姑大山中峰 - 不像预期的那么糟。
But reaching the farthest peak - Baigu Mountain East Peak (白姑大山東峰) - was tough, the bamboo got dense.
但到达最远的山峰 - 白姑大山东峰 - 很困难，箭竹变得密集。
When I finally reached it, my mission of completing all seven peaks was over.
当我终于到达时，我完成所有七座山峰的任务结束了。
Haha, not really.
哈哈，并不完全是。
My plan: continue on the east ridge if weather allows,
我的计划：如果天气允许，继续沿东稜前进，
if weather turned bad, return to main trail.
如果天气变坏，返回主步道。
The weather was perfect that day, so I continued northeast.
那天天气很完美，所以我继续向东北方向前进。
After a while, I started regretting it.
过了一会儿，我开始后悔了。
I was descending a very steep slope and had to stop and rethink.
我正在下降一个非常陡峭的斜坡，不得不停下来重新思考。
Was it worth returning back and leaving mountains by common trail
值得返回并通过普通步道离开山区
and stopping some car back to Puli for dinner with family?
并拦车回埔里与家人共进晚餐吗？
Or keep going?
还是继续前进？
I decided to keep going.
我决定继续前进。
The bamboo changed to a narrow ridge with bad landslide.
箭竹变成了有严重崩塌的狭窄稜线。
If I had an accident here, nobody could help me.
如果我在这里发生意外，没有人能帮助我。
On a small peak, I saw traces.
在一个小山峰上，我看到了痕迹。
The group probably cut bamboo to camp here.
那个队伍可能砍了箭竹在这里扎营。
I cannot imagine spending the night here.
我无法想像在这里过夜。
Definitely not alone, not today.
绝对不是独自一人，不是今天。
No trail, no marking, no obvious direction,
没有路径，没有标记，没有明显的方向，
no hope, just fear.
没有希望，只有恐惧。
Everywhere, finger-thick bamboo, hard to push through.
到处都是手指粗的箭竹，很难穿过。
I had GPS tracks from a recent group which went over,
我有最近一个通过这里的队伍的GPS轨迹，
but there was no way to recognize where I should crawl.
但无法识别我应该在哪里爬行。
I was heading toward Dong Gao Mountain (東高山)
我正朝着东高山前进
also called Ta Ban Mountain (塔班山).
也叫塔班山。
It was so hard.
太困难了。
Here you understand how important GPS navigation is.
在这里你会明白GPS导航有多重要。
You cannot determine direction clearly.
你无法清楚地确定方向。
Even with paper map and compass, the scale isn't enough,
即使有纸质地图和指南针，比例尺也不够，
it's very easy to take the wrong direction in dense bamboo.
在密集的箭竹中很容易走错方向。
I was prepared for this, but it was harder than expected.
我为此做好了准备，但比预期的更难。
Lucky for me, the weather was perfect.
幸运的是，天气很完美。
Petr: For little bit no bamboo.
Petr：暂时没有箭竹了。
(kicking old rusty can)
（踢旧生锈的罐头）
Some sections were pretty - open space or nice forest without bamboo.
有些路段很美 - 开阔的空间或没有箭竹的美丽森林。
And some places were ugly.
有些地方很丑陋。
I could see a lot of old trash from workers
可以看到很多旧垃圾
who logged forest here in the past.
来自过去在这里砍伐森林的工人。
The logging was stopped and mountain rats (山老鼠) activity is also controlled now,
伐木已经停止，山老鼠的活动现在也受到控制，
so all this trash and gear is quite old.
所以所有这些垃圾和装备都相当旧了。
I think the main hiking trail to Baigu is quite new.
我认为通往白姑的主要登山步道是相当新的。
From old maps, I have a feeling the original entry to mountains was this direction.
从旧地图来看，我有一种感觉，原来进入山区的入口是这个方向。
In past they didn't care about peaks but cared about access to forest areas for trees.
过去他们不关心山峰，但关心进入林区采伐树木。
From Baigu East Peak (白姑大山東峰) to Dong Gao Mountain (東高山):
从白姑大山东峰到东高山：
just 3.3 kilometers on the map.
在地图上只有3.3公里。
It took forever and took so much energy,
花了很长时间并耗费了很多力气，
but I finally reached the peak.
但我终于到达了山顶。
Petr: So tired.
Petr：好累。
I didn't celebrate long and detoured to one big pool - Ta Ban Chi (塔班池).
我没有庆祝太久就绕道去了一个大水池 - 塔班池。
Also possible to camp there.
那里也可以扎营。
Just the right time to get water, I took a moment to rest and cook tea.
正好取水的时间，我花了一点时间休息并煮茶。
From here, basically just five kilometers of descent toward the industrial road - Sheng Li Road (勝利路).
从这里，基本上只有五公里的下坡路通往产业道路 - 胜利路。
Should be easier, but it was still not easy.
应该更容易，但仍然不容易。
I trusted the GPS in my Garmin watch
我相信我Garmin手表中的GPS
and kept going through bamboo but also along edge of deep cliff.
并继续穿过箭竹，也沿着深崖的边缘前进。
On some views I could see in far my final destination,
从一些角度，我可以看到远处我的最终目的地，
village of my wife Lixing (力行).
我妻子的部落：马烈霸（力行）。
Petr: Please No More Bamboo. No More Bamboo!
Petr：拜托不要再有箭竹了。不要再有箭竹了！
Petr: Paolyta-B 保力達B
Petr：保力达B
Another "famous case" - university student Zhang Bowei (張博崴).
另一个“著名案例”- 大学生张博崴。
Found after 51 days in 2011, unfortunately dead.
2011年51天后被发现，不幸去世。
But evidence showed he survived many days after injury.
但证据显示他在受伤后存活了很多天。
This case raised many voices about SAR efficiency in Taiwan.
这个案例引发了许多关于台湾搜救效率的声音。
SAR is not perfect and never will be perfect,
搜救并不完美，永远也不会完美，
but in mountains, safety first depends on the hiker themselves.
但在山里，安全首先取决于登山者自己。
Then on assistance if really needed.
然后在真正需要时才是援助。
The lesson: If you really get lost
教训：如果你真的迷路了
you cannot leave mountains in random directions.
你不能随机地下切山区。
It often leads to difficult creeks with waterfalls.
这通常会导致有瀑布的困难溪谷。
All four cases had this in similar, they kept going down in random direction
所有四个案例都有相似之处，他们随机下切
and ended injured in creek.
最后在溪谷中受伤。
Died.
死亡。
GPS navigation is so important to me as well as gear choice.
GPS导航对我来说非常重要，装备选择也是如此。
Petr: Work house
Petr：工作屋
It's important to note - none of them were attempting this difficult route.
重要的是要注意 - 他们都没有尝试这条困难的路线。
They were all on the standard trail.
他们都在一般的路径上。
I finally reached Sheng Li Road (勝利路), real relief.
我终于到达了胜利路了，真正的解脱。
Just over one hour to sunset.
离日落只剩一个多小时。
I was on this road earlier this year with my gravel bike,
今年早些时候我骑公路车走过这条路，
also a two-day trip, so I'm familiar with it.
也是两天的旅程，所以我很熟悉它。
My plan: reach the main road, still ten kilometers away.
我的计划：到达主要道路，还有十公里远。
From calculation, not possible before dark.
根据计算，天黑前不可能到达。
Petr: Finally... Finally...
Petr：终于...终于...
Petr: Oh My God
Petr：天啊
Petr: 11 hours
Petr：11小时
Petr: Now 10km walk. At least 10km walk (will be 22km)
Petr：现在要走10公里。至少10公里（将是22公里）
This is the benefit of light packing - even in winter, my base weight is just five kilograms.
这就是轻量化的好处 - 即使在冬天，我的基本重量也只有五公斤。
I could walk fast, even jog.
我可以走得很快，甚至慢跑。
But I had a feeling I wouldn't be able to stop any car
但我有一种感觉，我无法拦到任何汽车
or truck to my final destination:
或卡车到我的最终目的地：
Lixing village (力行) - also called Marepa (馬烈霸) - still 12 kilometers more.
力行村 - 也叫马烈霸 - 还有12公里。
I remember there was a local store,
我记得那里有一家杂货店，
I bought snack and beer and decided to just walk to Lixing in the dark.
我买了零食和啤酒，决定在黑暗中走到力行。
It was actually quite nice and I little bit miss endurance sport
实际上还挺不错的，我有点怀念耐力运动
and the feeling when you are tired but getting closer to finish.
以及当你疲惫但越来越接近终点时的感觉。
Petr: This is how they reinforce the roads here. (Czech language)
Petr：这就是他们在这里加固道路的方式。（捷克语）
That day: 40 kilometers in my legs, fifteen hours of moving.
那天：我跑了40公里，移动了15小时。
Marepa (馬烈霸) is my wife's father's village, I would stay in our house there.
马烈霸是我妻子父亲的部落，我会住在我们那里的家。
Before the village, I visited my father-in-law at the cemetery.
在抵达部落之前，我先到墓园探望了岳父。
The grave is far in the corner behind bushes.
他的坟墓位在一个偏远的角落，藏在草丛后方。
I promised we would visit him again in April, tomb-sweeping day with the whole family.
我承诺我们会在四月再次拜访他，清明节和全家人一起。
I slept in our old village house very well.
我在部落的家里睡得很好。
Next day, I caught a ride back to Puli.
第二天，我搭便车回到埔里。
The driver could be hired by McLaren racing team.
司机可以被McLaren车队聘用。
Got back to Puli by noon to have lunch with my family.
中午回到埔里与家人共进午餐。
A couple days later, I biked back to Guguan (谷關) for my car.
几天后，我骑车回到谷关取我的车。
I really missed hiking, this kind of adventure.
我真的很想念登山，这种冒险。
But it reminds me: preparation before any mountain trip matters,
但它提醒我：任何登山旅行之前的准备都很重要，
and choosing the right gear,
选择正确的装备，
and choosing the right partner if you go with group.
如果和团队一起去，选择正确的伙伴(神队友很重要）。
The mountains are always there, but we have to be prepared for them.
山永远在那里，但我们必须为它们做好准备。